Yesterday, Chinese company Oli Baba dropped a brand new Open Weight Long Horizon mixture
of experts agent to coding model named Quen 3 coder, and amazingly, it's the first
open weight model that matches the programming performance of Clawed 4.
The undisputed leader of AI vibe coding tools at the present time.
Not only is the Quen 3 coder model open, but they also just released a brand new CLI
tool, forked from the recently open source Gemini CLI, that can take advantage of all
the model's agentic properties, like the ability to run, execute, and test your code
from the command line.
That's terrifying news for any programmer still left with a job, but mathematicians are
also on life support right now because both Google and OpenAI just achieved gold medals
in the International Mathematical Olympiad.
In today's video, we'll take a look at the latest AI breakthroughs and find out if
Quen 3 coder can actually compete with Clawed 4.
It is July 23rd, 2025, and you're watching the code report.
Just last week, the open model scene got a big upgrade with the Chinese Kimi K2, but
now Quen 3 coder pushes things even further.
The model was trained on 7.5 trillion tokens with a 70% code ratio.
In other words, it's seen a billion times more code than the average developer with 50
years of experience.
They even used their previous model to clean up noisy training data that the highly meta
process where AI basically determines which data to use to train itself.
When it comes to the training process, they use something called Long Horizon reinforcement
learning across 20,000 parallel environments.
The model actually tries to solve real world problems and real environments where it's
executing and testing code.
You can think of Quen's training infrastructure like a coding bootcamp with 20,000 graduates
all working on the same problem simultaneously, except they never get tired, never argue,
and never ask is this a breaking change.
And the end result speaks for itself in these benchmarks.
Based on this benchmark, Quen is outperforming Kimi and GPT 4.1 and almost on par with Clawed
4.
But doing so with a much smaller model size, which is important because the bigger the
model, the more electricity and GP use you need to run it.
What's also really impressive about Quen 3 coder is that it has a 256,000 token context
window that can stretch up to 1 million tokens.
But for reference, that's enough to hold the entire code base of most startups and all
of their technical debt.
Quen 3 coder is an open weight model, but if you think you're going to run it locally
on your laptop, it's time for a reality check.
To harness the full growth of the 480 billion parameter version, you would need tens of
thousands, if not hundreds of thousands of dollars worth of GPUs, along with a large wallet
to pay the electricity bill.
Realistically, to try it, you'd want to get an API key from a cloud provider, then hook
it up to the new Quen CLI tool, which again is a fork of the Gemini CLI.
Overall, this does appear to be a big leap forward for open coding models.
But I doubt that it will make much of a dent in Clawed's dominance in the coding world.
To be Clawed, a company needs to release a model that's not only open and inexpensive,
but that surpasses Clawed's capabilities by a significant margin.
Like OpenAI was recently supposed to release its own open model, but that's been delayed.
With the rumor for the delay, being that these Chinese models would absolutely crush it.
That's just one of many else taken by OpenAI recently, like Zuck gutting all of their talent.
But OpenAI did get a big win a few days ago when they achieved a gold medal in the International
Mathematical Olympiad.
What's funny though is that they made a dick move by announcing this before the closing
ceremonies of the event in order to overshadow Google and the press, who also achieved
gold medal level performance.
However, that ended up backfiring because it just made OpenAI look desperate.
But if you want to write really good code with AI, you need to check out CodeRabbit,
the sponsor of today's video.
Their free VS Code extension gives you advanced code reviews right in your editor.
And their new FixAll with AI feature passes all of CodeRabbit's review context directly
to the AI code agent of your choice.
This is so it can make all the changes for you.
This saves you from needing to click on each review comment yourself, giving you more
time to write even more broken code like a true artisan.
CodeRabbit is free to use in the IDE and work seamlessly with VS Code and Forex Light
cursor and wind serve.
Download it for free with the link below to try it out.
This has been the Code Report, thanks for watching, and I will see you in the next one.